Jonathan Krause Rare Newspaper and Magazine Collection 1648-1881 E302.1 .J76 E302.1 .J76
Lilly Library
- Colonial American and Early Republic Individuals
  - Thomas Paine
    - LETTER TO THE AUTHORS OF "LE REPUBLICAIN," Columbian Centinel, October 12, 1791 (Item 1027)
      Comments from Mr. Krause: One of the first Parisian reactions to the news that Louis had fled to Varennes. Le Republicain was a new Parisian newspaper, created by the Societe Republicain, whose members included Paine, Condorcet and Brissot. It lasted for only a few issues, but at that moment was in the vanguard of progressiveness. Paine's letter called for a French Republic, an idea even the Jacobins had not yet embraced. He was all for exiling Louis to America rather than killing him and having him become a catalyst for royalist discontent all over Europe (see Paine series). It prompted a debate with Abbe Sieyes (see Paine series) on the nature and value of monarchies and republics. Paine was moving the revolutionary ball forward, toward a constitution in the American mold. But principled men like La Fayette and Paine would give way to the radical Robespierre and his ilk. In America, Paine had been considered a leftist extremist. In France, he would come to be seen as counter-revolutionary. But on the political continuum he had always remained in the same position. He could be as practical as Hamilton, yet no one upheld the humanist ideals of the Enlightenment more than he.
    - ESSAY ON ESTABLISHING A U.S. MINT, American Museum Magazine, November 1791; Size: Small (Item 492)
    - DEDICATION LETTER FROM RIGHTS OF MAN, PART II TO LAFAYETTE AND PREFACE TO PART II, Independent Chronicle, June 28, 1792 (Item 493)
    - EXCERPTS FROM RIGHTS OF MAN, PART II, Independent Chronicle, July 12, 26, August 2, 23, 1792 (Item 494)
    - LETTER TO SOCIETY FOR CONSTITUTIONAL INFORMATION ON THE PUBLICATION OF THE RIGHTS OF MAN AND IMPENDING TREASON TRIAL, Columbian Centinel, August 18, 1792 (Item 994)
    - LETTER TO SECRETARY DUNDAS DEFENDING "RIGHTS OF MAN," Columbian Centinel, September 1, 5, 1792 (Item 495)
    - TWO PAINE LETTERS TO LORD ONSLOW ON THE RIGHTS OF MAN, Columbian Centinel, September 26, 1792 (Item 496)
    - LETTER TO SECRETARY DUNDAS ON INTERROGATION BY BRITISH AUTHORITIES, Columbian Centinel, December 12, 1792 (Item 497)
      Includes Joseph Priestly 539 and John Adams 11
    - FETED AND HONORED AND ELECTED DEPUTY TO FRENCH CONVENTION AND WASHINGTON OFFERED FRENCH COMMAND, Gazette of the United States, December 22, 1792 (Item 498)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 171
    - LETTER TO THE PEOPLE OF FRANCE ON WORLD REVOLUTION AND THE BROTHERHOOD OF MAN, American Daily Advertiser, December 28, 1792 (Item 499)
    - LETTER TO THE PEOPLE OF FRANCE ON WORLD REVOLUTION, Gazette of the United States, January 2, 1793 (Item 500)
    - ADDRESS TO THE FRENCH NATIONAL CONVENTION ON PROPRIETY OF BRINGING LOUIS XVI TO TRIAL, Independent Chronicle Extraordinary, March 8, 1793 (Item 501)
      Rare broadsheet.
    - REASONS FOR PRESERVING LIFE OF LOUIS XVI, Columbian Centinel, April 24, 1793 (Item 502)
    - LETTER FROM THOMAS PAINE TO GEORGE WASHINGTON, PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, 1797; Size: Small (Item 503)
    - DESCENT ON ENGLAND, Massachusetts Spy, April 4, 1798 (Item 504)
      2 copies (also John Adams 13)
    - LETTER ON POSSIBLE FRENCH WAR WITH UNITED STATES, Massachusetts Spy, July 25, 1798 (Item 505)
    - FIRST LETTER TO CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES AND LETTER TO WASHINGTON ATTACKING HIM, Boston Gazette, November 25, 1802 (Item 506)
    - FIRST LETTER TO CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES AND LETTER TO WASHINGTON ATTACKING HIM, Farmer's Museum, November 30, 1802 (Item 508)
      Includes Toussaint Louverture 442
    - SECOND LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Aurora, November 25, 1802 (Item 507)
      Includes Toussaint Louverture 441 and Napoleon Bonaparte 904 (November 25)
    - SECOND LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Boston Gazette, December 2, 1802 (Item 509)
      Includes Toussaint Louverture 441
    - THIRD LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Aurora, December 3, 1802 (Item 510)
    - THIRD LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Boston Gazette, December 9, 1802 (Item 511)
      Includes Anti-Paine 527
    - THIRD LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Farmer's Museum, December 21, 1802 (Item 513)
    - FOURTH LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Boston Gazette, December 16, 1802 (Item 512)
      Includes Anti-Paine 530
    - FOURTH LETTER TO THE CITIZENS OF THE UNITED STATES, Farmer's Museum, December 28, 1802 (Item 514)
      Includes Thomas Jefferson 275
    - PLAN FOR REVOLUTIONIZING AMERICA, Farmer's Museum, February 1, 1803 (Item 515)
    - REMARKS ON POLITICAL AND MILITARY AFFAIRS OF EUROPE, American Mercury, January 1, 1807 (Item 516)
    - LETTER ATTACKING CHEETHAM, American Citizen, October 29, 1807 (Item 517)
      See: Aaron Burr 62
    - LETTER ATTACKING CHEETHAM, New York Herald, November 28, 1807 (Item 518)
      Includes Stephen Decatur 64
    - MEMORIAL TO CONGRESS REGARDING REVOLUTIONARY WAR SERVICE, The Repertory, February 19, 1808 (Item 519)
  - Anti-Paine
    - PAINE AND JEFFERSON NO. 4, New York Herald, October 9, 1802 (Item 520)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 339
    - PAINE AND JEFFERSON NO. 5, New York Herald, October 13, 1802 (Item 521)
      See: Thomas Jefferson 268
    - PAINE AND JEFFERSON ANTI-RELIGION, New York Evening Post, October 15, 1802 (Item 522)
      See: Anti-Jefferson 346
    - PAINE AND JEFFERSON, New York Herald, October 16, 1802 (Item 523)
      See: Toussaint Louverture 437
    - SUMMARY OF PAINE'S CRIMES, Boston Gazette, November 29, 1802 (Item 525)
      Includes Toussaint Louverture 441 and Napoleon Bonaparte 904 (November 29)
    - ANTI-PAINE AND PAINE LETTER TO WASHINGTON, The Balance, November 30, 1802; Size: Small (Item 526)
    - PAINE AND WASHINGTON, Boston Gazette, December 6, 9, 1802 (Item 527)
      See: Thomas Paine 511. Excludes December 6.
    - ANTI-PAINE, The Balance, December 7, 14, 1802; Size: Small (Item 528)
    - PAINE'S DISMISSAL AS SECRETARY TO FOREIGN AFFAIRS COMMITTEE FOR IMPROPRIETIES AND MISCONDUCT, The Portfolio, December 11, 18, 1802 (Item 529)
      See: bound volume, The Portfolio, 1802-1803. Excludes December 11.
    - PAINE AND JEFFERSON, Boston Gazette, December 13, 16, 1802 (Item 530)
      See: Thomas Paine 512 (December 16)
    - ANTI-PAINE ON HIS ATTACKS ON WASHINGTON AND ADAMS AND HIS ATHEISM, The Portfolio, January 8, 15, 22, 1803; Size: Small (Item 531)
    - ANTI-PAINE, The Balance, January 11, February 22, May 17, June 7, 1803; Size: Small (Item 532)
    - ANTI-PAINE, The Balance, July 23, September 17, 1805; Size: Small (Item 533)
    - PAINE TRYING TO AMEND PENNSYLVANIA CONSTITUTION, The Balance, November 5, 1805; Size: Small (Item 534)
  - Joseph Priestly
    - DESTRUCTION OF PRIESTLY'S LAB AND RIOTING IN BIRMINGHAM, New York Journal, September 14, 1791 (Item 535)
      See: Thomas Paine 489
    - DESTRUCTION OF PRIESTLY'S LAB AND RIOTING IN BIRMINGHAM, Columbian Centinel, September 17, 1791 (Item 536)
      Includes Thomas Paine 490
    - LETTER TO INHABITANTS OF BIRMINGHAM, Massachusetts Spy, September 29, 1791 (Item 537)
      See: Thomas Paine 491
    - LETTER TO CONDORCET, Columbian Centinel, October 22, 1791 (Item 538)
    - LETTER TO FRENCH ASSEMBLY DECLINING MEMBERSHIP, Columbian Centinel, December 12, 1792 (Item 539)
      See: Thomas Paine 497
  - George Washington
    - INAUGURAL ADDRESS, American Museum Magazine, May 1789; Size: Small (Item 565)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE FOR 1789, New York Journal, January 14, 1790 (Item 575)
      First State of the Union Address in American history.
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Columbian Centinel, December 22, 1790 (Item 577)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Connecticut Courant, October 31, 1791 (Item 578)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Columbian Centinel, November 14, 1792 (Item 581)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Providence Gazette and Country Journal, December 14, 1793 (Item 584)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Independent Chronicle and Universal Advertiser, December 16, 1793 (Item 586)
      Includes George Washington 587
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Norwich Packet, December 19, 1793 (Item 588)
      Broadsheet supplement to the Norwich Packet.
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Columbian Centinel, November 29, 1794 (Item 592)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Massachusetts Spy, December 16, 1795 (Item 596)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 200
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Columbian Centinel, December 19, 1795 (Item 597)
    - STATE OF THE UNION MESSAGE, Columbian Centinel, December 14, 1796 (Item 603)
      See: George Washington 585
    - MAJOR WASHINGTON'S JOURNEY TO FORT ERIE, Gentleman's Magazine, June 1754; Size: Small (Item 542)
    - LETTER TO LIEUTENANT GENERAL THOMAS GAGE ON PRISONERS OF WAR, The London Gazette, September 19, 1775; Size: Small (Item 1047)
      Concern for the condition and treatment of American soldiers prompts this letter to the commander in chief of the British forces in North America a few months after the Battle of Bunker Hill. Washington threatens to treat British soldiers as Americans are treated. He says the rebel soldiers act from the noblest of principles, a love of freedom and their country, and that the rights of humanity are binding on the British.
      Also GENERAL GAGE'S LETTER TO WASHINGTON.
    - GENERAL ORDER PROHIBITING LOOTING AND PLUNDER. AND NEED FOR HUMANE TREATMENT OF CIVILIANS AND GATES LETTER, London Chronicle, April 5, 1777 - April 8, 1777; Size: Small (Item 543)
    - LETTER TO GENERAL HOWE REGARDING PRISONERS OF WAR, The Gentleman's Magazine, August 1777; Size: Small (Item 1048)
      One of the prisoners mentioned in the letter is Washington's enemy, General Charles Lee.
      See: Revolutionary War 1050
    - MANIFESTO IN ANSWER TO GENERAL BURGOYNE'S PROCLAMATION, Edinburgh Advertiser, August 29, 1777 - September 2, 1777; Size: Small (Item 545)
      Maybe a significant "unknown" Washington.
    - LETTERS TO GENERAL HOWE AND MANIFESTO, Gentleman's Magazine, September 1777; Size: Small (Item 544)
      Includes Revolutionary War 626
    - GENERAL GEORGE WASHINGTON AND GENERAL WILLIAM HOWE, BATTLE OF BRANDYWINE, The Edinburgh Evening Courant, November 8, 1777; Size: Small (Item 955)
    - LETTER ON SENDING GENERAL WAYNE TO SEARCH FOR FOOD AND ROCHAMBEAU LETTER, The London Chronicle, October 14, 1780 - October 17, 1780; Size: Small (Item 956)
    - LETTER TO CONGRESS ON ARNOLD AFFAIR, Edinburgh Evening Courant, December 6, 1780; Size: Small (Item 546)
      See: Alexander Hamilton 129
    - LETTERS INTERCEPTED BY BRITS TO GENERALS SULLIVAN AND LAFAYETTE ON ATTEMPT TO CAPTURE NEW YORK, London Chronicle, July 14, 1781 - July 17, 1781; Size: Small (Item 547)
      Just before Battle of Yorktown and possible disinformation for General Clinton.
    - LETTER TO CONGRESS ON YORKTOWN VICTORY, London Chronicle, December 20, 1781 - December 22, 1781; Size: Small (Item 548)
      Includes Alexander Hamilton 130
    - LETTER TO GUY CARLETON ON ASGILL CASE, Independent Chronicle, June 8, 1782 (Item 549)
      See: Thomas Paine 485
    - GENERAL ORDERS PROCLAIMING CESSATION OF HOSTILITIES IN REVOLUTIONARY WAR, London Chronicle, June 7, 1783 - June 10, 1783; Size: Small (Item 550)
      One of Washington's greatest works.
    - CIRCULAR LETTER TO THE SEVERAL STATES, Salem Gazette, July 24, 1783 (Item 551)
    - LETTER TO CONGRESS ON QUASHING NEWBURGH CONSPIRACY, London Chronicle, July 24, 1783 - July 26, 1783; Size: Small (Item 552)
    - CIRCULAR LETTER TO THE STATES AND FAREWELL TO THE PEOPLE AND ADDRESS TO HIS OFFICERS AND LETTER TO THE PRESIDENT OF CONGRESS ON COMPLAINTS OF THE ARMY, Gentleman's Magazine, August 1783; Size: Small (Item 553)
    - CIRCULAR LETTER CONTINUED, Gentleman's Magazine, September 1783; Size: Small (Item 554)
    - FAREWELL ORDERS TO THE ARMY, Salem Gazette, November 20, 1783 (Item 555)
    - FAREWELL ADDRESS TO CONGRESS, Gentleman's Magazine, March 1784; Size: Small (Item 556)
    - ADVERTISEMENT BY WASHINGTON OFFERING TO LEASE 30,000 ACRES ON THE OHIO AND GREAT KANAWA, Continental Journal, May 6, 1784 (Item 993)
      Comments from Mr. Krause: Washington, like Jefferson and Madison, was always looking for winning schemes regarding land speculation, as the majority of southern slaveholders had constant problems raising cash.
      Author: George Washington
    - LETTER OF ENDORSEMENT OF JAMES RUMSEY'S STEAMBOAT FOR POTOMAC COMMERCE, Massachusetts Centinel and the Republican Journal, October 9, 1784 (Item 557)
    - LETTER OF ENDORSEMENT OF JAMES RUMSEY'S STEAMBOAT FOR POTOMAC COMMERCE, Salem Gazette, October 12, 1784 (Item 558)
    - LETTER ON FARMING IS AMERICA'S HIGH CALLING, Pennsylvania Packet, October 2, 1786 (Item 559)
    - LETTER DECLINING PRESIDENCY OF SOCIETY OF CINCINNATI, Pennsylvania Packet and Daily Advertiser, April 27, 1787 (Item 560)
    - LETTER ON IMPORTANCE OF CONSTITUTION, American Museum Magazine, January 1788; Size: Small (Item 561)
    - GOING TO FIRST INAUGURAL AND CEREMONIAL ACTIVITIES AND ELECTION RESULTS, American Museum Magazine, April 1789; Size: Small (Item 562)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 119
    - GOING TO FIRST INAUGURAL ADDRESS AND CEREMONIAL ACTIVITIES AND ELECTION RESULTS, Gazette of the United States, April 25, 1789 - April 29, 1789 (Item 564)
    - LETTERS TO THE PRESIDENT AND EXECUTIVE COUNCIL OF PENNSYLVANIA AND TO TRUSTEES AND FACULTY OF THE UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, American Museum Magazine, April 1789; Size: Small (Item 563)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 120
    - ADDRESSES TO THE SENATE AND HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES AND LETTERS TO MAYOR AND CITIZENS OF ALEXANDRIA AND BALTIMORE AND PHILOSOPHICAL SOCIETY OF CINCINNATI AND MAYOR OF PHILADELPHIA, American Museum Magazine, May 1789; Size: Small (Item 566)
    - LETTER TO MAYOR AND COUNCIL OF PHILADELPHIA, Massachusetts Centinel, May 2, 1789 (Item 567)
      One of the most fervent religious utterances of Washington's political life.
    - GOING TO FIRST INAUGURAL ADDRESS AND CEREMONIAL ACTIVITIES AND ELECTION RESULTS, Massachusetts Centinel, May 2, 1789 (Item 568)
      See: George Washington 567
    - LETTERS TO THE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH AND BISHOP OF METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH (AND FIRST ACT OF CONGRESS), Gazette of the United States, June 3, 1789 - June 6, 1789 (Item 569)
    - LETTERS TO THE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH AND BISHOP OF METHODIST EPISCOPAL CHURCH (AND FIRST ACT OF CONGRESS), American Museum Magazine, November 1789; Size: Small (Item 572)
    - ADDRESS TO WASHINGTON COLLEGE ON EDUCATION, Pennsylvania Packet and Daily Advertiser, July 15, 1789 (Item 570)
      Washington's only bequest in his lifetime to an institution of higher learning was to Washington College.
    - LETTER TO QUAKERS ON RELIGIOUS TOLERANCE AND ANOTHER TO CONNECTICUT ASSEMBLY AND NEW ENGLAND TOUR, New York Journal and Weekly Register, October 29, 1789 (Item 571)
    - LETTERS TO CONGREGATIONAL MINISTERS OF NEW HAVEN, PRESIDENT OF HARVARD, TOWN OF BOSTON, MAYOR OF HARTFORD, New York Journal and Weekly Register, November 5, 1789 (Item 573)
    - LETTER TO SYNOD OF REFORMED DUTCH CHURCH, Gazette of the United States, November 25, 1789 (Item 574)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 125
    - LETTER TO THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF VIRGINIA, Gazette of the United States, May 1, 1790 (Item 576)
      See: John Adams 5
    - LETTER ON LOUIS AND FRENCH CONSTITUTION, National Gazette, March 8, 1792 (Item 579)
    - EARLY PROCLAMATION ON WHISKEY INSURRECTION, Columbian Centinel, October 3, 1792 (Item 580)
    - HENRY KNOX (SECRETARY OF WAR) RESPONDS TO FAILED ST. CLAIR EXPEDITION, GENERAL DUMOURIER LETTER WARNING OF PRUSSIAN ARMY, Gazette of the United States, November 17, 1792 (Item 957)
    - PROCLAMATION ON RECENT CRIMES AGAINST CHEROKEES, Dunlap's American Daily Advertiser, December 19, 1792 (Item 582)
    - NEUTRALITY PROCLAMATION, Concord Herald, May 16, 1793 (Item 583)
    - TWO LETTERS AND JEFFERSON LETTER AND FRENCH CONSTITUTION, Gazette of United States, September 4, 1793 (Item 952)
    - MESSAGE TO HOUSE ON RELATIONS WITH FRANCE AND GENET AFFAIR (AND STATE OF THE UNION ADDRESS), Columbian Centinel, December 14, 1793 (Item 585)
    - MESSAGE TO HOUSE ON RELATIONS WITH FRANCE AND GENET AFFAIR, Independent Chronicle, December 16, 1793 (Item 587)
      See: George Washington 586
    - LETTER DEALING WITH THE APPOINTMENT OF JOHN JAY, Courier of New Hampshire, May 15, 1794 (Item 958)
    - FIRST PROCLAMATION ON WHISKEY REBELLION, Columbian Centinel, August 16, 1794 (Item 589)
      Includes French Revolution 953
    - SECOND PROCLAMATION ON WHISKEY REBELLION, Columbian Centinel, October 4, 1794 (Item 590)
    - LETTER TO HENRY LEE ON WHISKEY REBELLION, Columbian Centinel, November 8, 1794 (Item 591)
    - WASHINGTON RETURNS FROM WHISKEY REBELLION, Courier of New Hampshire, November 22, 1794 (Item 959)
    - PROCLAMATION ON DAY OF THANKSGIVING AFTER WHISKEY REBELLION, Connecticut Courant, February 2, 1795 (Item 593)
    - LETTER ON THE CONSTITUTION, Gazette of the United States, August 15, 1795 (Item 594)
    - LETTER ON JAY TREATY AND CONSTITUTION, Columbian Centinel, August 19, 1795 (Item 595)
    - LETTER TO EDMUND RANDOLPH DEFENDING HIS HONOR AND JAY TREATY AND RANDOLPH RESIGNING IN DISGRACE, The Herald, December 30, 1795 (Item 598)
    - LETTER ON THE FRENCH REVOLUTION, Columbian Centinel, January 16, 1796 (Item 599)
    - MESSAGE TO HOUSE ON JAY TREATY CONCERNING CONSTITUTION AND A TREATY WITH SPAIN, Connecticut Journal, April 7, 1796 (Item 600)
      Discussion of Constitution and separation of powers.
    - MESSAGE TO HOUSE ON JAY TREATY CONCERNING CONSTITUTION AND A TREATY WITH SPAIN, Connecticut Courant, April 11, 1796 (Item 601)
    - FAREWELL ADDRESS, Federal Gazette and Baltimore Daily Advertiser, September 21, 1796 (Item 602)
      Most famous address in American history.
    - FAREWELL ADDRESS, The Times, November 9, 1796 (Item 960)
    - LETTER FROM PIERRE ADET, Massachusetts Spy, November 16, 1796 (Item 954)
      See: John Jay 235
    - FAREWELL LETTER TO HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES AND THEIRS TO HIM AND LETTER TO THE LEGISLATURE OF VERMONT, Massachusetts Spy or Worcester Gazette, December 28, 1796 (Item 604)
    - LETTER UPON LEAVING OFFICE CONCERNING THE FORGERIES OF HIS CORRESPONDENCE IN 1777, Morning Chronicle, May 30, 1797 (Item 605)
    - LETTER RELUCTANTLY ACCEPTING COMMAND OF THE ARMY AGAIN DURING THE CRISIS WITH FRANCE, Massachusetts Spy or Worcester Gazette, July 25, 1798 (Item 606)
    - LETTER TO BALTIMORE MASONS, Massachusetts Spy or Worcester Gazette, December 12, 1798 (Item 607)
    - LETTER TO THE VIRGINIA MILITIA DURING QUASI-WAR WITH FRANCE, Federal Gazette and Baltimore Daily Advertiser, December 15, 1798 (Item 1078)
      Washington was in retirement and the very last thing he would want was to be pulled away from Mount Vernon. He was an old man by the standards of the day at sixty-six. But he would do his duty if there was an invasion of the homeland by the French during this quasi-war period. Until that unlikely time, he suggested to Adams that Hamilton was the best man to whip the army into shape. There was bad blood between Adams and Hamilton, which erupted in the 1800 campaign and may have cost Adams the presidency. Adams strongly objected, insisting Washington orchestrate the preparations. Washington wouldn't budge with Adams ultimately capitulating to Washington's desire. This is a stirring, patriotic letter yet anchored by Washington's fervent hope there would be no serious hostilities. This is one of this last letters to make it into the newspapers and Washington had only about a year to live. The Washington Papers indicate that after the second paragraph of the letter, there was a short paragraph missing from this newspaper which said, "Upon this ground have I accepted my commission; and upon this ground I trust that every true American will be prepared to defend his Country against foreign encroachments; and to perpetuate the blessings which he enjoys under his own Government."
      ALSO JOHN ADAMS LETTER TO THE SENATE
    - FUNERAL OF WASHINGTON AND ADAMS' PROCLAMATION, Connecticut Courant, January 13, 1800 (Item 608)
      See John Adams 24
    - MARTHA WASHINGTON LETTER ON DEATH OF GEORGE, Salem Gazette, January 17, 1800 (Item 609)
  - Phyllis Wheatley
    - AMERICA'S FIRST BLACK SLAVE POET WRITES POEM "ON RECOLLECTION" AND SHORT BIOGRAPHY, Gentleman's Magazine, September 1773; Size: Small (Item 610)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 98
  - James Wilson
    - FAMOUS SPEECH ON NECESSITY OF THE UNION AND RATIFICATION OF THE CONSTITUTION, Connecticut Courant and Weekly Intelligencer, October 22, 1787 (Item 540)
- Colonial American and Early Republic Topics
  - Pre-Revolutionary War
    - SAMUEL ADAMS CIRCULAR LETTER, New York Gazette, July 11, 1768 (Item 611)
    - REVOLUTIONARY ACTIVITIES, The Boston Evening Post, September 3, 1770 (Item 612)
    - CONTINENTAL CONGRESS AND RESOLVES, Pennsylvania Packet, September 5, 1774 (Item 613)
    - CONTINENTAL CONGRESS AND PETITION TO THE KING, Gentleman's Magazine, January 1775; Size: Small (Item 614)
  - Revolutionary War
    - BATTLE OF LEXINGTON AND CONCORD, London Chronicle, June 15, 1775 - June 17, 1775; Size: Small (Item 615)
    - GUNPOWDER PLOT, London Chronicle, July 20, 1775 - July 22, 1775; Size: Small (Item 616)
    - DECLARATION OF CAUSES AND NECESSITY OF TAKING UP ARMS AND BATTLE OF BUNKER HILL, Gentleman's Magazine, August 1775; Size: Small (Item 617)
    - KING GEORGE SPEECH TO WHICH PAINE RESPONDED IN COMMON SENSE, Gentleman's Magazine, October 1775; Size: Small (Item 618)
    - BATTLE OF NEW YORK, Supplement to Gentleman's Magazine, Supplement, 1776; Size: Small (Item 619)
    - PRE-NEW YORK AND CANADA, London Chronicle, August 13, 1776 - August 15, 1776; Size: Small (Item 620)
    - BATTLE OF NEW YORK AND HOWE'S MEETING WITH FRANKLIN AND ADAMS, London Chronicle, November 16, 1776 - November 19, 1776; Size: Small (Item 621)
    - GENERAL HOWE PROCLAMATION, London Chronicle, November 19, 1776 - November 21, 1776; Size: Small (Item 622)
    - BRITISH ADVANCE ON PHILADELPHIA, London Chronicle, January 7, 1777 - January 9, 1777; Size: Small (Item 623)
    - BATTLE OF PRINCETON, London Chronicle, March 8, 1777 - March 11, 1777; Size: Small (Item 624)
    - WAR ACTIVITIES AND GENERAL HOWE, London Chronicle, April 3-April 5, 1777, June 5-June 7, 1777; Size: Small (Item 625)
    - LETTER FROM WASHINGTON TO GENERAL HOWE ON PRISONERS OF WAR, The Gentleman's Magazine, August 1777; Size: Small (Item 1050)
      Mention of General Charles Lee, one of the prisoners, who had badmouthed and undermined Washington in aid of securing his job as commander of the Continental Army. Still Washington named Fort Lee after him. At the Battle of Monmouth in 1778, Lee ordered a premature retreat and was relieved of his command by Washington for disobeying oders and insubordination.
      Also GENERAL HOWE'S LETTERS TO WASHINGTON ON PRISONERS OF WAR
      Also GENERAL BURGOYNE'S PROCLAMATION, a hyperbolic attack on American rebels, supposedly the catalyst for Washington's Manifesto. (See: Washington 544, 545)
      Also GENERAL BURGOYNE'S LETTER TO SECRETARY OF STATE FOR THE COLONIES GEORGE GERMAIN ON THE TAKING OF FORT TICONDEROGA After this success would come the disaster of the Battle of Saratoga, convincing the French the Americans could win, precipitating their entrance into the war.
      Also GENERAL HOWE IN JERSEY AND GENERAL CORNWALLIS ON STATEN ISLAND
    - WASHINGTON LETTERS AND MANIFESTO, Gentleman's Magazine, September 1777; Size: Small (Item 626)
      See: George Washington 544
    - FRANKLIN LETTER TO LORD NORTH AND RECOGNITION OF U.S. BY FRANCE, Connecticut Courant, May 26, 1778 (Item 627)
      See: Benjamin Franklin 102